Guide to the Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1960-1975: Interviews, 2010-2019 MS2388
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1960-1975: Oral history interviews
2010-2019
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2388
59 digital object(s)
Lessons of the Sixties is an organization dedicated to documenting the efforts and lessons learned by local DC Metropolitan Area activists, students, organizers and those who dreamed of building a better world through new ideas, political advocacy, local organization building, and other means in the years 1960-1975. Since 2010 the Institute for Policy Studies has served as the organizational home for the Lessons of the 60s providing office space and infrastructural support. This collection contains the 59 oral history interviews conducted from 2010-2019. The orginals, raw footage and display versions are housed on the Special Collections preservation server. The digital object links for each interview are to the Youtube channel maintained by the organization.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lessons of the Sixties, 2019 November 20 (2019.101).
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by interviewee last name.
Historical note
Lessons of the Sixties is an organization dedicated to documenting the efforts and lessons learned by local DC Metropolitan Area activists, students, organizers and those who dreamed of building a better world through new ideas, political advocacy, local organization building, and other means in the years 1960-1975. The organization's goal is to make materials easily available for future activists, historians, students, writers, and media producers. Members have given presentations on their findings in order to facilitate direct dialogue between generations of social justice activists. One of the most significant contributions are the oral histories it conducted between 2010-2019 with local activists. Lessons of the Sixties has the objective of focusing on key local and national movements and events of this period in which D.C-area-based residents were involved. These topics include, but are not limited to, 1963 March on Washington, anti-Vietnam War organizing, Black power movement, civil rights movement, DC statehood movement, early battles against gentrification, fair housing, international solidarity, May Day 1971, peace movement, Stop the North Central Freeway/3 Sisters Bridge, student activism for peace and civil rights, and the Women's movement.
Since 2010 the Institute for Policy Studies has served as the organizational home for the Lessons of the 60s providing office space and infrastructural support.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the 59 oral history interviews conducted from 2010-2019. All donated orginals, raw footage and mp4 versions are housed on the Special Collections preservation server. The digital object links for each interview direct users to the Youtube channel maintained by the organization.
Related Materials
Lessons of the Sixties donated materials that are found in several GW collections. The links to the related collection's finding aids are below. Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1960-1975: James G. Stockard papers finding aid Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1960-1975: Personal papers finding aid Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1963-1990: Joann Malone papers finding aid To go directly to the assistance provided by the Lessons of the 60s from their website: To watch all the video interviews conducted by the Lessons of the Sixties project, go to the Lessons of the Sixties conducted interviews page If your focus is word searching interviews and document collections use Lessons of the Sixties keyword lists.
- Interview: Aaronson, Larry, 2018 January 26; MS2388
  Biographical / Historical
  Larry Aaronson grew up in Washington DC, where he began a teaching career after college. He cut his political teeth in the local civil rights movement, moving later to Cambridge, MA to teach in public schools for over forty years. Larry maintains that he has learned more from his hundreds of students than they ever learned from him.
  Keywords
  Keywords provided by the donor for Larry Aaronson inteview: Segregated Washington DC in 1940s - 1950s - 1960s, Spingarn High School: the true condition of DC public education, SNCC leader Marion Barry as mentor, Black history and Jim Crow and Reconstruction information as spur for high school activists, DC Bus Boycott, Bill Simon and Charlie Cheng and DC Teachers Union, Institute for Policy Studies (IPS) as important meeting place, Senator Ernest Gruening, The Cardozo Project: empowering students and teachers, Liberation Pedagogy, 1968 riots/uprising - impact on city, Emergency Committee on the Transportation Crisis (ECTC) as response to crisis, Montgomery County Public Schools (MCPS), Coleman Report, 1969 Moratorium, Harvard School of Education, Social Studies as crucible of education, Personal realization that questioning authority is essential part of education for students and teachers.
- Interview: Alperovitz, Gar, 2014 June 13; MS2388
  Gar Alperovitz has had a distinguished career as a historian, political economist, university professor, activist, writer, and government official.
  He is the author of critically acclaimed books on the atomic bomb and diplomacy. The books, written in the 1960s and the 1990s, convincingly challenged long-held claims by President Truman and other defenders of early U.S. atomic policy that the dropping of atomic bombs on Hiroshima and Nagasaki was necessary to save thousands of American troops' lives. Rather he wrote, citing newly declassified evidence, U.S. policymakers based their strategy toward the Soviet Union on the judgment that the atomic bomb, once demonstrated, would provide leverage in negotiating the postwar world order.
  From 1966 to 1968, while a Fellow at the Harvard Institute of Politics, Alperovitz developed the "Vietnam Summer" campaign centered on canvassing and teaching to motivate undecideds and non-activists into taking action against the war. Although his role only became known more than 45 years later, Alperovitz in 1971 worked with Daniel Ellsberg to keep the publication of the Pentagon Papers going -- after the initial publication by The New York Times was halted by a court challenge by the Nixon administration -- by secretly arranging to hand off portions of the report to one news outlet at a time, beginning with The Washington Post.
  In the decades since then, the D.C.-based Alperovitz has worked on issues relating to inequality and participatory democracy. In that regard, he is the president of the National Center for Economic and Security Alternatives and is a founding principal of the Democracy Collaborative, a research institution developing "practical, policy-focused, and systematic paths toward ecologically sustainable, community-oriented change and the democratization of wealth."
  Biography provided by the donor.
  General
  Keywords provided by the donor for Gar Alperovitz interview: Racine Wisconsin, Parents Democrats, Cancer Society, Football high school, University of Wisconsin, History Department, William Appleman Williams, Scholarships, Harvard, Yale, NYU Law School, Didn't go, Fred Harvey Harrington, Fellowship to Berkeley, Student Union president (U. Wisconsin), Saul Landau, Student Life and Interest Committee, Labor Youth League, Communist Party, Pete Seeger, George Mosse historian, Berkeley, Masters in economics, Hyman Minsky, Marshall Scholarship, England, Bob Kassettiere, HUAC (House Unamerican Activities Committee), American expansionism, American imperialism, Rosa Luxembourg, Joan Robinson, Left Post-Keynesian economics, Cambridge, Kings, PhD with Joan Robinson, Marcus Raskin, Dick Barnet, Arthur Waskow, Bill Proxmire, Henry Reuss, Legislative assistant to Kastenmeier, Kennedy years, John F. Kennedy was cold warrior, Richard Nixon, Missile Gap, Cold War, Cambridge England), PhD. thesis, Gaylord Nelson, Gulf of Tonkin, Atlantic City, Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, Community Development Corporations (CDC), Kari (daughter), Peace Research Institute, Arthur Waskow, Christopher Jencks, New Republic, Richard Barnet, Disarmament, Atomic bomb, Cuban Missile Crisis, Todd Gitlin, Kastenmeier, Cambridge (MA), Cuban Missile Crisis, Erich Fromm, Hans Morgenthau, Hannah Arendt, David Riesman, Paul Goodman, Civil rights movement, Peace movement, Women's movement, SNCC (Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee), Ivanhoe Donaldson, Tina Smith, Frankfurt Institute, Anarcho-communal vision (Raskin), Civil rights, Vietnam War, Call to Resist, Antiwar movement, Gulf of Tonkin, Karl Hess, Cambridge Institute, Christopher Jencks, Kalorama, Belmont Place, Adams Morgan, Racine Wisconsin, Labor town, Industrial town, Israel, Kibbutz, Community Development Corporations, State socialism, David Morris, Karl Hess, Fish farming, Corporate capitalism, Neighborhood technology, Jeff Faux, Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO), Bedford-Stuyvesant Corporation, Community Development Corporations, New Communities Inc., Micro-socialism, John McClaughry, Community Self-Determination Act, CORE (Congress on Racial Equality), Floyd McKissick, Roy Innis, Public banks, "Notes Toward a Pluralist Commonwealth", Staughton Lynd, Neighborhood corporations, Worker-owned, State banks, Regional — Tennessee Valley Authority, Atomic bombing of Hiroshima book, Martin Luther King, Mississippi, Bob Moses, Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, Vietnam War, Carter administration, Paul Krugman, Dean Baker, Charlie Rose, Cambridge Institute, Jeff Faux, National Center for Economic Alternatives, Youngstown Steel, University of Maryland, Benjamin Barber, "Strong Cities Strong Democracy", Jessica Gordon Nembhard, Marcus Raskin, Economic stalemate stagnation decay, New economy movement, Co-ops, Land trusts, James Gustav (Gus) Speth, Academy of Management (conference topic), "Is Capitalism Over — and What Do We Do About it?", Davos, Ellen Brown, California state banking, Joe McCarthy era, Conservatives in the 1940s, European social democracy, Weak U.S. labor movement.
- Interview: Aronica, Lou, 2014 April 25; MS2388
  Long-time activist Lou Aronica is one of the Founding Fathers of the continuing D.C. statehood movement. Back in the early 1970s, Lou was one of the co-founders of the D.C. Statehood Party (now Statehood Green), along with such veterans of local civil rights and social justice struggles as Julius Hobson, Hilda Mason, Josephine Butler and Charles Cassell. More than any other Washingtonian, Lou has served as a leading tactician and the institutional memory for the statehood movement and as an historian of the District's long struggle to have the same rights as all Americans in the 50 states.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Lou Aronica interview: Sam Smith, Progressive Review, D.C. Gazette, Tower City, PA, anthracite region, University of Maryland, graduate studies, International House, Americans for Democratic Action (ADA), staff director, ADA, 1961, non-communist Left, Julius Hobson, Congress on Racial Equality (CORE), Mid-Atlantic chapter, Associated Community Teams (ACT), Julius Hobson, Safeway, Hahn's Shoe Store, picket lines daily, D.C. Transit, secretarial schools, rats, Hobson ploys, police spying, Roy Chalk, D.C. Transit, fare increase, Julius Hobson, refused to pay fare, METRO, Lyndon Johnson, appointed DC Council, CORE, ADA, Hubert Humphrey, D.C. Fair Housing Council, International Self-Help Housing Association, Rural America, Sharecroppers Fund, Marion Barry, home rule, "home fool", Walter Fauntroy, Constitutional amendment, voting rights, statehood, Congress, Julius Hobson, Sam Smith, freeways, proposed 6 major interstate highways, appointed City Council, Rep. Joel Broyhill, Virginia, federal payment, independent City of Georgetown, District of Columbia smaller, Alexandria, pre-Civil War, D.C. governor, legislature, freed slaves, Boss Shepherd, Florida Avenue original boundary, 3-person commission, Army Corps of Engineers, commission form, 1865-1967, John F. Kennedy, home rule bill, Lyndon Johnson, Barry Goldwater, House of Representatives, District of Columbia Committee, House District Committee, Chairman, Rep. (John) McMillan (D-South Carolina), home rule bill, Rep. B.F. (Bernie) Sisk (D-California), Joseph Rauh, Senator Wayne Morse (D-Oregon), Rep. Adam Clayton Powell (D-N.Y.), Rep. Edith Green (D-Oregon), House Education and Labor Committee, Elementary and Secondary Education Act, Bernie Sisk, Lyndon Johnson, executive order, appointed mayor/commissioner, city council, Walter Washington, freeways, Broyhill threats on freeways, police riot, D.C. council chambers, arrests, Julius Hobson, on school board, arrested, Bruce Terris, chairman DC Democrats, arrested, Harriet Hubbard, Dupont Circle, right to vote for president, elected school board, elected non-voting delegate, Julius Hobson, non-voting delegate, Rev. Walter Fauntroy, Martin Luther King, Jr., SCLC (Southern Christian Leadership Council), Channing Phillips, Joseph Yeldell, "Coalition of Conscience", Sam Smith, Norman Mailer, Jimmy Breslin, DC Gazette, statehood article, Rep. Ron Dellums (D-California), introduced statehood bill, Hawaii, Alaska, Ernest Gruening, Alaska territorial governor, Compact Commission, Statehood Commission, federal city, police jurisdictions, U.S. Constitution, no minimum size federal District of Columbia, Maryland, Virginia, National Airport, Aronica wrote original Dellums bill, reciprocal income tax, Pentagon, Bill #1776, Ed Guinan, CCNV (Community for Creative Nonviolence), Statehood initiative, November 1980, Statehood Constitutional convention, D.C. Constitution adopted, basic mistake, prominent people omitted, Joe Rauh, Gilbert Hahn, John Hechinger, Washington Post, Constitution passed by voters, Sam Smith, progressive D.C. Constitution, House of Representatives, statehood vote in House, Rep. Bernie Sisk, D.C. Statehood Party, Norville Perkins, head, Board of Elections, Julius Hobson, D.C. Statehood Party ballot status
- Interview: Becker, Eddie, 2016 April 07; MS2388
  Lifelong activist who has used his technical and research skills in the service of movements for social change in the U.S. and around the globe.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Eddie Becker inteview: Eddie Becker, 1970 Alternative Media Conference, underground newspapers, radio, Videofreex, Tom Weinberg, Radical Software, Sony PortaPaks, a revolution, Eddie's youth, old radios, shortwave, Rockaway NY, "the list", parents, NYC Teacher's Union, after high school, travels, Washington DC, group houses, Quicksilver Times, bomb-making issue, SOURCE Catalog 1970, Federal City College Video Center, Roberto Barzini, May Day 1971, National Student Association, video coverage, edited at Videofreex NYC, goes to Italy, worker's councils, tenant organizations, student organizations, do it yourself video, playback in the community, Italian communists, return to NY, the draft, indicted, guilty, 2 yrs probation, anti-war movement in disarray, Italians send him to National Archives, society changes, Freedom of Information Act (FOIA), WWII records open at NARA, CIA and the Vatican, book AMERICA IN ITALY, same techniques in Vietnam, Fields of Plenty, 1982 technology changes, CNN, Nicaragua, Peru, Eritrea, 1975 Perpetual Research Group, local housing activist, group house, red lining, Adams-Morgan Organization, Seaton Street, coops, community reinvestment, INDIE MEDIA, 1989 Seattle, WTO, Washington DC BREAKING THE BANK, action against the World Bank, Blagden Alley media hub, partnership for civil justice, footage as evidence, entrapment tactic, lessons learned?, every generation must learn its own lessons, paranoia, how to spot an infiltrator, COINTELPRO, War On Drugs, intergenerational divide.
- Interview: Benson, Sally, 2017 May 12; MS2388
  Sally Benson is a long-time antiwar activist who determined, after college, to live "a meaningful and independent life." Originally from Western Massachusetts, she found herself drawn to Asia, and in 1966 secured a teaching position in Vietnam through the International Volunteer Service. She lived and worked in Saigon and experienced the 1968 Tet Offensive up close, with her landlady warning her to cancel a planned visit to a friend the very night that the National Liberation Front troops moved in. Returning to the US in 1969, she and her partner Steve Nichols purchased a house in Washington, DC and became stalwarts of the local anti-war movement there, as well as well as working with national anti-war organizations through the end of the war. Today Sally still works on issues of reconstruction and reconciliation, travelling frequently to Southeast Asia.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Sally Benson interview: International Volunteer Service (IVS), Tet Offensive, Fred Branfman, Steve Nichols - draft refuser, Indochina Resource Center (IRC), Fred Branfman and Project Air War, Indochina Mobile Education Project (IMEP), IMEP staffers: Sally Benson, Jacqui Chagnon, Don Luce, Jean-Pierre Dubuis, Roger Rumpf, Bob Minnick, Issues addressed by IMEP, Other organizations Sally worked with: Clergy and Laity Concerned CALC), Women Strike for Peace (WSP), Medical Aid to Indochina (MAI), Indochina Peace Campaign (IPC), 1977 American women's trip to Vietnam
  ​
- Interview: Blum, William, 2015 October 30; MS2388
  (1933-2018) - William Blum left the State Department in 1967, abandoning his aspiration of becoming a Foreign Service Officer because of his opposition to the U.S. war in Vietnam. He then became one of the founders and editors of the Washington Free Press, the first "alternative" newspaper in the capital. Beginning in the early 1970s, Bill was a freelance journalist in the United States, Europe and South America. His stay in Chile in 1972-1973, writing about the Allende government's "socialist experiment" and its overthrow in a CIA-designed coup, led him to a heightened interest in what his government was doing in various parts of the world. In the mid-1970's, he worked in London with former CIA officer Philip Agee and his associates on their project of exposing CIA personnel and their misdeeds. His book on U.S. foreign policy, Killing Hope: U.S. Military and CIA Interventions Since World War II, first published in 1995 and updated since, received international acclaim. Noam Chomsky called it "far and away the best book on the topic." Blum, who died in late 2018, was also the author of four other books, the last one being America's Deadliest Export: Democracy — The Truth About U.S. Foreign Policy and Everything Else (2013). His books have been translated into more than 15 languages. Bill's lifelong work was to educate the American public about the reality of US foreign policy and its global impacts.
  Keywords provided by the donor for William Blum interview: Vietnam, U.S. State Department, Brooklyn, Washington Free Press, Chile, Allende government, Philip Agee, CIA, "Killing Hope: U.S. Military and CIA Intervention Since World War II", Iraq, "America's Deadliest Export: Democracy", "Rogue State", Osama bin Laden, RT network, Brooklyn, City College of New York, computer programmer, IBM, State Department, foreign service exam, Vietnam War, Adlai Stevenson, Washington Peace Center, Marxist study group, State Department, Washington, D.C. Committee to End the War in Vietnam, Washington Free Press (WFP), "My Life at the State Department", Co-founders, Frank Speltz, Ann Speltz, Art Grosman, Mike Grossman, Q Street, 17th and 18th offices, hippies, typical WFP issue, anti-war, dope, marijuana, acid, civil liberties, civil rights, film, theater reviews, calendar of events, fire in hallway, FBI, disruption/spying, vendors fined, Columbia records, FBI, printers, Long Island printer, Seymour Hersh, FBI break-in, CIA, Quicksilver Times, Salvatore (Sal) Ferrera, CIA headquarters, taking down license plate numbers, tape recorder, Pentagon, Blum's CIA file, Quicksilver Times, Washington Free Press, politicos/hippie factions, Carl Bernstein, abortion counseling, Washington Free Press, Dr. (Milan) Vuitch (abortion doctor), Silver Spring, MD, Vuitch arrested, march on Pentagon 1967, Dr. Benjamin Spock, Marcus Raskin, Norman Mailer, levitate Pentagon, Quicksilver Times, Sal Ferrera, CIA, DMV offices -- Maryland, Virginia, D.C., Sal Ferrera, CIA informant, Philip Agee, Agee's book, Ferrera and CIA, Ferrera spying on Agee, typewriter bugged, Institute for Policy Studies (IPS), Karl Hess, informants/agents, Jan Tangen, Irwin Bock, Max Philip Friedman, House committee, Jerry Rubin, Rennie Davis, maharishi person, Art Grosman, Frank Speltz, anti-war movement, protest fatigue, 2003 -- protests against upcoming Iraq War, U.S. invaded Iraq, U.S. ignored tens of millions protesters, Syria, Bernie Sanders, Hugo Chavez, Jill Stein, Barack Obama, Bernie Sanders, Hillary Clinton, war hawk, Bobby Kennedy, Barack Obama, "Killing Hope", Moscow, No internet, library research, London, Australia, Liberation News Service, 1 Thomas Circle movement building, Students for a Democratic Society (SDS), Marshall Bloom, Ray Mungo, Pacifica radio, Chilean refugees, San Francisco, Santiago, Chile, Panama, Salvador Allende, Chilean coup, Charles Horman, Frank Teruggi, Berkeley Barb, Quicksilver Times, Terry Becker, Sal Ferrera, Quicksilver Times office, 17th Street NW
- Interview: Boylston, Hope and Lynda Tredway, 2016 September 22; MS2388
  Lynda Tredway and Hope Boylston met in the middle 60s when both enrolled as undergraduates at George Washington University. Both had a strong interest in politics, Lynda influenced by John Kennedy's call to action and Hope planning to study anthropology and see the world to "escape her privileged life." A life-long friendship developed from their shared experience as roommates, activists, mothers and educators, with Hope's human rights work around Chile informing her later teaching career in Pennsylvania, and Lynda's teaching experience and expertise making her a national authority on public secondary education, training and professional development. Hope authored a book, "Hoy Locos," about her time in Chile. Lynda, now retired from teaching at Berkeley and back in DC, is an accomplished artist and is currently working on an art project that addresses lynching.
  Biographies provided by the donor.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Hope Boylston and Lynda Tredway interview: DC in the mid-60s: what it was like, Activism on campus: charismatic anthropology professor fired, Lynda starts tutoring, begins "new life" as an educator, Hope in South America: Ecuador & Chile, Hope gains "revolutionary consciousness" from Ecuador experience, Lynda begins habitually "thinking against mainstream", Early women's movement, the Pill and abortion, Hope moves to Chile, translates "Our Bodies, Ourselves", Lynda observes poverty, racism as educational problems while teaching in DC schools, Anti-war activities step up, Lynda and Hope "on the streets", Difficulties of coalition work in 70s, Hope's and Lynda's "Lessons of the 60s"
- Interview: Brecher, Jeremy, 2013 October 12; MS2388